Guide to the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection, 1695-1955 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- P-R
  - Phillips, John papers, 1743-1798
    Collection consists of oversized parchment deeds and indentures pertaining to land in what was called the "Northern Liberties" of Philadelphia in the 18th century. Included is a map [ca. 1778?] of land owned by William Coates, a Revolutionary officer and Justice of the Peace for the township of North Liberties. Of particular interest is the plot of land on Coates Street designated as the property of Benjamin Franklin. This is the plot mentioned in Franklin's last will and testament as "my pasture-ground which I have in Hickory Lane, with the buildings thereon..." The remainder of the collection consists of land indentures made by several different parties.
  - Pickens, Andrew papers, 1801-1827
    Includes correspondence; a memorandum of agreement between Pickens and David Files regarding a loan from Pickens to Files; financial papers relating to the operation of Pickens' plantation in Alabama; a mortgage bond; and an Agricultural Memorandum Book (1822-1826) which discusses the clearing of land for planting cotton and corn, describes the seeds he used, and includes several pages of accounts. Pickens also comments on his visits to Cahaba, Alabama, and the flood which occurred while it was the state capitol.
  - Pickens, Francis Wilkinson papers, 1806-1868, undated
    Twenty-three items of correspondence in this collection mainly concern political matters after 1832, when Pickens became openly active in the nullification controversy. Several letters from 1833 deal with Colonel Pickens' efforts to promote the state oath of allegiance and to raise and provision a contingent of his Edgefield constituents. Of particular interest is a letter detailing the types and amounts of military supplies available to various local volunteer groups. The finest items in the collection are three lengthy letters from James Hammond to Pickens in 1839-1840. Some correspondence is personal. Also included are some legal documents and miscellany items. The collection is housed in Box 7 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Picture Collection, after 1860
    The major portion of this collection of pictures consists of 53 cartes de viste, dating from the 1860s. Most of them are pictures of Civil War generals. Many of these cartes bear a U.S. postage stamp, indicating that they were produced before or during the period Sept. 1, 1864-Aug. 1, 1866, when all such photographs transported in the U. S. mail were subject to this form of government tax in order to raise additional wartime revenue. Only five of them have not been identified. Also included in this collection are 30 engravings, most of them of prominent American statesmen. Included in the collection are engravings of Kit Carson, Samuel P. Chase, Horatio Gates, and members of Abraham Lincoln's cabinet. Two non-person pictures include an undated print of the Charlotte Female Institute and an 1863 print of Camp Vermont, Virginia during the Civil War. As of April 2008, these items are located on 6th 16:B.
  - Pillow, Gideon Johnson papers, 1861
    Collection contains largely routine items pertaining to Gen. Pillow. They concern army supplies and skirmishes around, Charleston, Mo.
  - Poetry, Miscellany papers, 1848-1865
    Miscellaneous poems, most of the creators are unidentified. These items are housed in Box 7 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Polk, James K. papers, 1840-1845
    Includes a written statement from the Sherriff of Bradley County, Tennessee in addition to two unrelated letters. These items are housed in Box 7 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - G. P. Putnam's Sons records, 1886-1908
    Correspondence illustrating the publication and investment relationship of Theodore Roosevelt with the G. P. Putnam’s Sons publishing house. Among the items are four notes from Roosevelt to George Haven Putnam, discussing business affairs and Roosevelt’s reasons for breaking off business with the company. Two other notes discuss Roosevelt’s North Dakota cattle ranches. Other correspondence comes from Douglas Robinson, a New York real estate man and partner with Roosevelt in an investment venture with the Putnam firm. Robinson questions the timing and amount of his returns.
  - Revolutionary War autographs, 1776-1784
    Individual autographs of Revoluntionary War soldiers. These items are located in Box 7 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Roosevelt, Theodore papers, 1916, undated
    Includes a note written by Roosevelt to Judge M. W. Morrow and a thank-you note to a Dr. Mullowney. These items are located in Box 7 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
- S
  - Saye, James Hodge papers, 1790-1896
    Chiefly correspondence of the Saye family. Early letters trace James Saye's progress through the Columbia Theological Seminary in Decatur, Ga. Other correspondence details his pastorships in Henry County, Ga., in Unionville and Fairforest, S.C., then in Chester County, S.C. Several letters are from fellow ministers, and discuss Presbyterian Church matters and national politics. Later correspondence is chiefly between the six Saye daughters and their mother, Rebecca Saye (McJunkins), and concern domestic issues and Reconstruction in the South. A letter by Rebecca details the genealogies of the Saye and McJunkins families. One letter (1883) addressed to James Saye from a professor at Davidson College recounts college affairs. Other documents include legal papers, including one Freedmen's Bureau document of 1866 which indentures an orphaned African-American boy to Rev. Saye for fourteen years.
  - Schriver, Edmund papers, 1834-1853
    Correspondence to Edmund Schriver from two West Point fellow graduates, Robert Selden Garnett and William Wallace Smith Bliss. Topics deal in great detail with army life in general, including politics, scandals, and events; the Cherokee War; the war with Mexixo, including the battles of Palo Alto, Resaca de la Palma, Monterey, and Buena Vista; Bliss' role as chief-of-staff to General Zachary Taylor, and, later, as private secretary to President Taylor in Washington; and the reaction to Taylor's election in 1848.
  - Scott, Winfield papers, 1822
    This collection contains 2 items: an 1822 letter from Scott to John Floyd in Washington and Floyd's response to Scott. The letters discuss military publications. These items are located in Box 8 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - South Carolina, Miscellany papers, 1787-1934
    This collection includes miscellaneous items related to South Carolina. Correspondence makes up the bulk of the collection and correspondents include Strom Thurmond and Arthur P. Hayne. Also included are financial documents such as receipts and printed material such as pamphlets for The Crosby Military Institute in Feasterville, S.C. and reports regarding S.C. government. The material is housed in Box 8 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Sherman, William T. papers, 1863-1869
    Included in this collection are correspondence and orders written by Sherman as well as his address to the 1869 graduating class of the United States Military Academy at West Point. These items are located in Box 8 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Sims, Joseph Starke papers, 1819-1903 and undated
    Correspondence, financial records, legal documents, clippings, account books, commissions, addresses and speeches, and a diploma. Correspondence concerns chiefly cotton growing, trade and prices; slaves who worked in cotton fields; financial matters; Washington, D.C. politics, with references to Henry Clay and John Calhoun; state and national politics; descriptions of newly settled areas of Mississippi and California; and a cholera outbreak in Charleston (1832). Civil War letters detail problems at Fort Sumter (1861), and often refer to economic difficulties and shortages in South Carolina. Other Civil War letters are also written from Manassas, Alabama, and Mississippi. One letter from Mississippi details the desperation of women left alone and unable to flee before the advancing Union Army. Post-war letters reveal the problems of Reconstruction in South Carolina. Many of the letters are to Sims' wife Jane Emily Sims (Farnandis). Includes an autobiographical letter from J. K. Paulding, author and statesman, and an essay by the same, entitled "The history of Uncle Sam and his boys." Some of Sims' addresses and one of the legal documents concern Nullification, which Sims' strongly supported. Other documents include an obituary for Franklin H. Elmore, plantation and general account books, and some material on Sims' student days at South Carolina College (ca. 1817-1819), which includes a letter to his brother in 1819 "in defence of General Jackson," and his "treatment of the Indians."
  - Sims, William papers, 1770-1860
    Correspondence, financial papers, and legal documents, concerning William Sims' extensive plantation holdings in South Carolina. Includes two account books. Correspondence is primarily related to business matters, including cotton trade and prices; the price and availability of slaves; and the beginnings of a textile industry on the plantation. Local and state politicians in South Carolina are often mentioned, as is the general economic plight of the Southern planter in the period (ca. 1819-1830), and currency problems in the state (ca. 1826-1830). One personal letter effusively describes newly settled land in Mississippi and the quality of the cotton grown there. Detailed financial papers form the bulk of the collection, and concern the cotton trade (including weights, bale numbers, shipping, prices, and sales), and household and plantation expenses. Legal papers are confined to deeds, documents of land litigation, military commissions, and documents relating to slaves, such as indentures and lists of slaves on the plantation. Also includes genealogical information on the Sims family.Cotton grower in Union County, South Carolina.
  - Samuel Slater & Sons records, 1839
    Letters and financial papers from shops and individuals who bought cloth from and sold cloth to Samuel Slater and Sons. Many of the merchants discussed problems in cash availability, as the letters were written during one of the peaks of the 1839 banking crisis.
  - Sloan, Edwin R. papers, 1861-1863
    Civil War letters from Edwin R. Sloan, a private in Company F, 1st Regiment, N.C. Cavalry, chiefly to his wife Sarah in N.C. Letters span Sloan's military career from 1861 to ten days before his death in September, 1863. Some of Sloan's letters are written from Camp Marsh; Camp W. S. Ash; Washington Co., Md.; Culpepper, Va.; Hanover Junction, Va.; Upperville, Va.; and Raccoon Ford, Va. Letters contain accounts of camp life, deprivations, and rumors and predictions about the war. The author expressed strong Southern sentiments. One letter written in 1861 provides an account of Confederate soldiers fraternizing with the United States soldiers under a flag of truce and being entertained and fed by them. Sloan also described scouting expeditions along the Potomac; Union soldiers burying Confederate dead at Upperville; his sorrow on the death of General Jackson; and his attempt to buy a furlough to come home. In August and September of 1863, Sloan reported of rumors that North Carolina would return to the Union. He expressed his desire for peace, but not at the expense of returning to the Union.
  - Smith, Samuel Francis papers, 1831-1936
    Signed holograph copy of four verses of "America," written by Samuel Francis Smith, and a pamphlet published by American Autograph Shop, containing a facsimile of the first and last verses of "America"; a copy of the entire hymn as printed for the celebration by the Boston Sabbath School Union of Independence Day in 1931; printed copies of two other hymns; a copy of an address to the children by the Rev. Wisner; and a facsimile of notes made by a Dr. Jenks during the celebration.
  - Stephens, William papers, 1780-1811
    Letters pertaining to Stephens' business and legal affairs, as well as a letter in which he complains to Governor Richard Howley about the lack of a jail in Augusta and the consequent lawlessness in the county. One letter to Abraham Mims in Newport, R.I., was written from the Stephens family vacation home in Providence.
  - Sternes, A. L. papers, 1861-1862
    Two letters from Sternes to his wife, expressing affection and concern, and a third letter from Lieutenant L. A. Potts informing Mrs. Sterned of her husband's death on August 2, 1862.
  - Stuart, J.E.B. papers, 1861-1863
    This addition to the Jeb Stuart Papers includes the following: General Order no. 14 issued under Stuart's order and signed by Heros von Bourke; an announcement of the death of Captain Redmond Burke at Shepherdstown, Va.; letters to Major Martin concerning cavalry operations in Va.; and a number of letters to Stuart's wife, Flora, in Wytheville(?), Va. One group of letters to her is from Harper's Ferry and concerns men and arms for an upcoming battle. Others discuss the Union troops' advance, Stuart's advancement in the C.S.A., his concern for his wife's well-being, and efforts to arrange for her a visit to his camp. One holograph message from Stuart states that General Jackson wishes to see Rufus Barringer.
  - Sumner, Charles papers, 1862-1868
    This collection includes four letters to Sumner, including one from W. H. Seward and one from Edwin Stanton. These items are housed in Box 8 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
- T-Z
  - Tappan, Mason Weare papers, 1857-1865
    Letters to Mason W. Tappan primarily concerning Republican politics. Correspondents include Schuyler Colfax, N.H. senator John Parker Hale, and Amos Tuck. Also includes letters on legal matters from U.S. Attorney General Caleb Cushing.
  - Tucker-Coalter Family papers, 1794-1821
    Collection of letters chiefly written by John Randolph, known as "Randolph of Roanoke," to various family members, including his half-sister Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, John Coalter, and Henry St. George Tucker. Other correspondents include St. George Tucker, Edmund Randolph, and William Wirt, Attorney General of the U.S. Topics cover family matters, Washington and Virginia politics, legal matters, illnesses, and child-rearing. Another letter mentions "automata," mechanical men Randolph observed while a law student in Philadelphia.
  - Tyler, Erastus Barnard, 1856-1863
    Primarily letters written during the Civil War by Tyler to his parents from camps in the Kanawha Valley of Virginia as well as posts near Washington, Va., and Culpepper, Va; and the field at the Battle of Gettysburg. These letters reflect Tylers's service under General Rosecrans as well as the movements and engagements of his forces. One letter was written from Fort Randall, Nebraska Territory in 1858.
  - Tyler Family papers, 1834-1881
    Papers pertaining to President John Tyler and his family. Petition, 1834, from prominent residents of King and Queen County, Va., asking Tyler to endorse their candidate for the U.S. Senate; letter of recommendation (1841) from Burke Washington concerning a naval candidate, Alexander Jones; letter from John Tyler, Jr. (?) in reply to H. C. Corbin; letter written by Julia (Gardiner) Tyler (1881) in reply to an autograph collector.
  - U. S. Dept. of the Navy records, 1802-1877
    This collection of correspondence, directed to the Secretaries of the U. S. Navy, consists largely of recommendations for young men desiring appointments to the Naval Academy and other Naval positions. Other contents include incidental messages on Navy finance, notes and letters on legislation affecting the Navy, reports on Naval operations in Gibraltar and elsewhere, on sailors' conduct and on provisioning. As of April 2008, this material is located on 6th 16:C.
  - U. S. War Department records, 1814-1865
    A detailed list of a cavalry troop; a letter from Tenn. governor Willie Blount to Capt. James Cowan of the U.S. Rangers, concerning the Creek Wars in Tenn.; a letter from Mass. governor Caleb Strong to Adj. Gen. John Brooks referring to appointments to the War Dept.; four letters of recommendation, two of these directed to Joel R. Poinsett, then Secretary of War; a property document (1865) from the Freedmen's Bureau; and a grant of military bounty lands to a Mrs. Sarah Woolley.
  - Van Buren, Martin papers, 1837-1840
    This collection includes a letter (1840) to Van Buren from his daughter-in-law, Angelica as well as a land grant from 1837 to Benjamin Crumpacker of La Porte County, Indiana.
  - Van Ness, William Peter papers, 1805
    Van Ness was the second in Aaron Burr's duel with Alexander Hamilton and was indicted as an accessory to Hamilton's murder. He fled to New York and later became judge of the U.S. Circuit Court for a New York district. The letter is from Burr from Chilicothe. Here, Burr asks Van Ness to meet him in Berkeley Springs and instructs him to contact certain people in New York and Philadelphia.
  - Vinson, Fred M. papers, 1944-1946
    Included are four short pieces of correspondence addressed to Harry L. Dalton from 1844-1946. A large folder of clippings and miscellany includes articles on Vinson and the Treasury, a long statement delivered to the House Ways and Means Committee (Oct 1, 1945), as well as clippings and the Life magazine cover story on Vinson's swearing in as Chief Justice (1946).
  - Virginia, Miscellany papers, 1761-1864
    Miscellaneous items related to the Commonwealth of Virginia. Collection includes mainly land grants and correspondence. This material is located in Box 9 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Voigt, Edward papers, 1839-1874(bulk 1839-1845)
    Predominantly correspondence between Edward Voight and Caroline Voigt of Warren Farm, Chester County, Pa., during their courtship and early years of marriage. A majority of the letters are from Edward's hand. The correspondence between the couple concerns Edward's work as a bookkeeper, and later his mercantile business in Philadelphia; religious devotion and piety; social engagements; the couple's courtship and wedding plans; and travel, particularly by rail between Chester County and Philadelphia. These letters provide a perspective on gender roles and relations during the mid-nineteenth century insofar as they reflect the propriety and etiquette expected of the young couple, as well as Edward's expectations concerning Caroline's religious devotion and her independence on this matter.
  - Washington, George papers, 1775-1939
    Facsimilies of Washington correspondence and several engravings of both Washington and his wife Martha. These items are located in Box 9 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - White, R. L. C. papers, 1852-1861
    Collection is composed of autographs solicited and collected by R.L.C. White of Lebanon, Tennessee. Most of the signatures are from government figures in Washington. A note is also included, dated March 10, 1860, written from Washington, DC by Charles Francis Adams in response to a request for an autograph.
  - Whiteside, Thomas papers, 1821-1864
    Gentleman's pocket book, bound in suede with flap. Scanty accounts fill only a small portion of the book. "Thos. Whiteside--His book" is written on the front, and the name is mentioned several times inside. Book appears to have originally been owned by Jesse Broomfield whose initials appear above Whiteside's on the cover and the earliest entries bear his name. Broomfield was one of the original sponsors of the Ebenezer Academy (1834) near Rock Hill, SC.
  - Wilkes Family papers, 1816-1877
    Correspondence of members of the Wilkes family, consisting primarily of letters to Charles Wilkes (1798-1877), naval admiral, and of many letters that he wrote. Letters from prominent scientists such as James Renwick, Asa Gray, James D. Dana, and Jean L. R. Agassiz also appear in the papers, as does correspondence of naval officers, Congressmen, diplomats, and cabinet secretaries, especially Secretaries of the Navy. Included among the numerous subjects mentioned in the papers is the exploring expedition that Wilkes commanded to the Antarctic continent, islands of the Pacific Ocean, and the American Northwest coast from 1838-1842. There is a lot of family correspondence from various members of the Wilkes family which include two wives of Charles Wilkes. Other types of material in the collection are legal papers, financial records, printed material, writings, account books, a science notebook written by Wilkes' son Edmund in 1847, and a volume entitled, "Notes Relative to the Fijii [sic] Islands," written by Charles Wilkes. These items make up part of the Charles Wilkes Papers.
  - Willard, Henry A. papers, 1834-1890
    Most of the collection deals with Willard's ownership of the famous Willard Hotel. Extensive correspondence documents the comings and goings of clients at the hotel, as well as repair and financial matters there. Legal and financial papers are concerned with the hotel, as well as with Willard's other interests as founder of the National Safe Deposit, Savings and Trust, Co., as a member of the D.C. Board of Public Works, and as chairman of the Board of Trustees for the District of Columbia Reform School in the 1870s and 1880s. Willard received appointments signed by the President every three years. Thus, the signatures of Grant, Hayes and Cleveland appear here. A few personal items are included, such as an icy exchange between Henry and his brother Joseph C. Willard. Of interest is a long document to the Supreme Court of the District of Columbia which details the feud between the two brothers.
  - Williams, William Augustus papers, 1825-1867 and undated
    Collection consists of correspondence, notebooks, and miscellaneous papers of Colonel William Augustus Williams of Wilmington and Charlotte, N.C. Correspondence includes letters from Henderson C. Lucas, Williams's nephew, who was wounded at Gettysburg while serving in the 11th Regiment of the N.C. Infantry; and letters related to Williams's efforts to bring the wounded Lucas to Charlotte. Other correspondence is primarily of a financial nature. A letter from William Henry Heyward describes the effects of reconstruction on South Carolina Coastal planters. A letter from Rev. Aldert Smedes mentions the financial hardships suffered by St. Mary's School in Raleigh, N.C. and is written on stationery describing the school's tuition and curriculum. Notebook dated 1827 contains exercises in penmanship and renderings of famous poems, while one dated 1825 is an arithmetic practice book. Also included are papers related to the Raleigh City Guards.
  - Wirt, William papers, 1810-1854
    Papers of William Wirt and of Elizabeth Washington (Gamble) Wirt, including letters concerning William's law practice; a letter relating an anecdote concerning William Wirt, Henry Clay, and a General Parker; fragmentary letter, 1833, from Wirt to a law student at the University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, discussing education; and a fragment of Wirt's draft of his biography of Patrick Henry. Correspondence of Elizabeth Washington (Gamble) Wirt, wife of William, and two sons, Dabney Carr and William C., concerns the purchase and sale of land, a debt incurred by Wirt for land he planned to develop in Florida, the widow's financial affairs, the erection of a monument to her husband, and other family matters.
  - Woodruff, Isabella papers, 1768-1865